Guide to the Tamar Carroll Oral Histories on Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) OH.066
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamar Carroll Oral Histories on Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!)
1990, 2003-2005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Carroll, Tamar
OH.066
1 Linear Feet in 2 card boxes
21 CDs
2 DVD-R
1 audiocassette
7.87 Gigabytes in 15 computer files
Tamar Carroll is a history professor at Rochester Institute of Technology in Rochester, New York. Between 2003 and 2005, while a PhD candidate in history at the University of Michigan, Carroll conducted oral histories with members of Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) for her dissertation. The Tamar Carroll Oral Histories on Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) document Carroll's work conducting oral histories with members of WHAM! between 2003 and 2005 as part of her dissertation project. The collection consists of audio recordings of individual interviews, and video recordings of group interviews and a WHAM! reunion.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restricitions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Tamar Carroll in circa 2008. The accession number related to this acession is 2009.092.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Some audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Access DVDs and CDs for audiovisual materials in the collection are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only.
Biographical Note
Tamar Carroll is a history professor at Rochester Institute of Technology in Rochester, New York. Between 2003 and 2005, while a PhD candidate in history at the University of Michigan, Carroll conducted oral histories with members of Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) for her dissertation. Her dissertation, "Women's Activism, Identity Politics, and Social Change in NYC, 1955-1995", focused on three social movements in New York City between the 1950s and 1990s. One of the movements was the partnership between the AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP) and WHAM! to improve health care, fight homophobia and misogyny, and to support People with AIDS in the 1980s and 1990s. These interviews were also used as the basis for her book Mobilizing New York: AIDS, Antipoverty, and Feminist Activism (UNC Press, 2015).
Scope and Contents
The Tamar Carroll Oral Histories on Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) document Carroll's work conducting oral histories with members of WHAM! between 2003 and 2005 as part of her dissertation project. The collection consists of audio recordings of individual interviews, and video recordings of group interviews and a WHAM! reunion. Transcripts for some audio interviews are available by request and one interview is available in transcript form only. The oral histories document the experiences of former members of WHAM!, the work of the organization, and the impact these experiences had on the members. The individual interviews and the group interview focus on what brought people to WHAM!, the ways in which they participated in the group, the aims of WHAM!, direct actions and protests in which the narrators participated, and coalitions formed between WHAM! and other organizations, in particular the AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP) and the Reproductive Rights Coalition. The video recording of the WHAM! reunion documents an event held at the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives at New York University in 2005. The event included a panel of former WHAM! members, each of whom discusses the topics included in the oral history interviews; an overview of her project by Carroll; and discussion with the audience, most of whom were members of WHAM!.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in alphabetical order by last name of the narrator, with the group events listed at the end of this arrangement.
Related Materials
For more information about WHAM! see the Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) Records (TAM 162)
For more information about Mary Anne Staniszewski, see the Exit Art Archive (MSS 343)
Appraisal
An interview belonging to "Elizabeth M." from Carroll's Mobilizing New York was accidentally donated with the collection and was deaccessioned. The interview was previously attributed to Elizabeth Meixell pre-processing.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted.
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Women's rights.; Women -- Political activity -- United States.; Women -- Health and hygiene -- United States.; Reproductive rights -- United States; Women radicals -- United States -- Interviews; Oral history.; Pro-choice movement -- United States.; Carroll, Tamar; WHAM! (Organization: 1989); ACT UP (Organization)
- Cain, Shannon, November 3, 2004; cuid34422
  Biographical Note
  Shannon Cain, born 1964, is an activist, writer, and visual artist. She lived in New York City between 1988 and 1995 and was a member of Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) from 1991 to 1994.
  Scope and Contents
  This interview was conducted by Tamar Carroll over the telephone on November 3, 2004 with Shannon Cain. Carroll made notes but the interview was not recorded. Cain discusses her background in feminism and activism, her introduction to Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!), and her experiences as a member of WHAM!. She explains that she learned about WHAM! in 1991 and describes her experience at WHAM!'s Chain of Fools action in Columbus Circle. She describes the energy of the WHAM! meetings and the different types of people she met. She discusses the way in which WHAM! meetings worked, her work as treasurer for a year, specific direct actions created by WHAM!, and her work with abortion clinic defense. She also discusses her work with Action Tours, an affinity group formed with WHAM! and AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP) members.
  - Original Media (Box 1, Cd TW_OH_066_1)
  - Interview Index, TW_OH_066_ER_15
- Curtis, Diane, July 19, 2004; cuid43173
  Diane Curtis is a professor of legal studies at the University of Massachusetts, Amherst. She was a member of the AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP) and a member and co-founder of the Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!). She graduated from New York University and received her law degree from New York University School of Law.
  This interview was conducted by Tamar Carroll on July 19, 2004 at an unspecified location. The interview was recorded in a crowded location and is often hard to understand, as there is a lot of background noise. The interview covers Diane Curtis's membership and participation in the AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP) and the Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!). Curtis discusses her introduction to activism in the early 1980s when she came out as a lesbian and became involved in gay rights issues, first in California and then after her move to New York City (NYC) in 1985, and the way in which ACT UP's use of the Silence=Death posters led her to join the organization. She discusses the way in which the Webster v. Reproductive Health Services Supreme Court decision in 1989 crystallized for her how abortion rights were not safe and that this decision led her to join the Reproductive Rights Coalition (RRC). She discusses the differences between members of the RRC who belonged to more conservative organizations and younger members coming from ACT UP, and how this led to the creation of WHAM!. She explains the way WHAM! meetings worked, the fact that they used Robert's Rules of Order to run the meetings, and the ways in which this made it difficult for people to hijack meetings and made it easier for more shy people to participate. Other topics include WHAM! agendas apart from abortion access, the similarities between ACT UP and WHAM!, and the way in which WHAM! affected the later careers of its members, including Curtis.
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cd TW_OH_66_3)
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd TW_OH_066_9)
- Davis, Susan, March 3, 2004; cuid34421
  Susan Davis was born in Rochester, New York and was raised by her mother. Davis grew up surrounded by feminist ideology. She graduated from Mount Holyoke College in South Hadley, Massachusetts in 1964. She was a member of the Committee to End Sterilization Abuse (CESA), a founding member of the Committee for Abortion Rights and Against Sterilization Abuse (CARASA), and a member of Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!).
  This interview was conducted by Tamar Carroll on March 3, 2004 at an unspecified location. The interview follows Susan Davis's involvement with the Committee to End Sterilization Abuse (CESA), which later became the Committee for Abortion Rights and Against Sterilization Abuse (CARASA). Lastly, the interview details her time with the Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!).
  Davis explains that she became politically active because of the Vietnam War, discussing the ways in which protests enlivened her historical, sociological, and feminist ideals and propelled her to participate in women's health causes. She discusses her membership in the Committee to End Sterilization Abuse (CESA) and her role as a founding member of the successor to CESA, the Committee for Abortion Rights and Against Sterilization Abuse (CARASA) in 1977. She explains how both CARASA and CESA were instrumental in bringing about federal sterilization guidelines in 1979. Davis also discusses her participation in the founding of WHAM! in 1989, direct actions in which she participated during her membership in WHAM!.
  An electronic transcript of this interview is also available by request.
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cd TW_OH_066_1)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_066_ER_22
- de Mause, Neil and Mindy Nass, October 15, 2005; cuid34417
  Neil de Mause was a political activist who was primarily involved in reproductive freedom activism in the late 1980s and throughout the 1990s. de Mause attended Wesleyan University and became involved in civil disobedience in 1989. He lived in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York and it was there he was introduced to the activist group Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!). He was an early member of the Reproductive Rights Coalition and was heavily involved in the production of the WHAM! Newsletter.
  Mindy Nass was a political activist in the late 1980s and 1990s in Brooklyn. Nass received her undergraduate degree from the State University of New York at Albany and entered the Graduate School at Hunter College in 1992. She became involved in reproductive rights activism during her time as an undergraduate. She joined the National Organization for Women (NOW), and took a course at the Learning Alliance on Women's Activism. After college, she became involved in WHAM! serving on the Newsletter Committee for WHAM!. Nass met de Mause, whom she later married.
  This interview was conducted by Tamar Carroll on October 15, 2005 at an unspecified location. The interview focuses on Mindy Nass and Neil de Mause's activism in the late 1980s into the late 1990s centered around Brooklyn, New York and their work with Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) on reproductive freedoms and rights. In the interview, Nass and de Mause discuss how they got into activism, how they met, what committees they worked on, individual experiences within WHAM! among other activist organizations, and other people they worked with in the scope of their activism.
  The audio of the interviews degrades at certain points and there is substantive background noise throughout the interview.
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cd TW_OH_066_7)
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cd TW_OH_066_8)
  - Access Copies (Box Shared Tamiment 091, Cd OH-66-004-01, OH-66-004-02)
- Dorow, Heidi, April 13, 2004; cuid34418
  Heidi Dorow attended school at Hampshire College in Amherst, Massachusetts until she relocated to New York City in the summer of 1988. She was involved in AIDS activism and civil disobedience through the AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP) and Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!).
  This interview was conducted by Tamar Carroll on April 13, 2004 at Judson Memorial Church in Manhattan, New York. In this interview, Heidi Dorrow begins by describing her move to New York City from Hampshire College in Amherst, Massachusetts in order to become involved with the AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP). Dorrow goes on to describe her involvement in demonstrations and educational events planned by ACT UP in New York City and in the eastern United States, her eventual split with ACT UP over ideological differences related to the scope of the organization's activism and its relationship to other reproductive health and reproductive justice issues, and her involvement in early activism by Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!).
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cd TW_OH_066_3)
  - Preservation Copies (Box 1, Cd OH-66-005-01, OH-66-005-02)
  - Access Copies (Box Shared Tamiment 091, Cd OH-66-005-01, OH-66-005-02)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_066_ER_16
- Griffin, Brian, March 16, 2004; cuid34413
  Brian Griffin is a gay rights and women's rights activist. After receiving a graduate degree in mixed media art from the University of California, Berkeley in 1989, Griffin moved to New York City. There, he became involved in the activist organizations AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP) and Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!). He was a central member of the Church Ladies for Choice in the early 1990s, an organization that he continued to be involved with through the taping of this interview.
  Scope and Contents Note
  This interview was conducted by Tamar Carroll on March 16, 2004 at an unspecified location. In the interview, Brian Griffin discusses his involvement with Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!), the group's activities, and its dissipation. Griffin also discusses the gay community during the AIDS crisis and his involvement with AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP). Much of the interview concerns the Church Ladies for Choice, a group of gay activists who dressed in drag and counter protested anti-abortion demonstrations, including their formation and specific activities.
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cd TW_OH_066_3)
  - Preservation Copies (Box 1, Cd OH-66-001-01, OH-66-001-02)
  - Access Copies (Box Shared Tamiment 091, Cd OH-66-001-01, OH-66-001-02)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_066_ER_14
- Kaltman, Elizabeth -- Interview Notes, August 31, 2004; TW_OH_066_ER_23
- Luciano, Dana -- Transcript, September 20, 2004; TW_OH_066_ER_24
- Matuschka, July 19, 2005; cuid34423
  Matuschka, born Joanne Motichka in 1957, is a photographer and former member of Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!). In 1991, she was diagnosed with breast cancer and underwent a mastectomy and chemotherapy. While in chemotherapy, she learned that a lumpectomy could have been performed but that her doctor did not inform her of this option. She brought a medical malpractice suit against her doctor and became involved with a number of breast cancer and women's organizations, including SHARE, 1 in 9, the National Organization for Women (NOW), National Alliance of Breast Cancer Organizations (NABCO), and WHAM!.
  This interview was conducted at Matuschka's apartment by Tamar Carroll on July 19, 2005. The interview covers Matuschka's introduction to activism, her experiences with breast cancer and how it led to her joining Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!), and her experiences with WHAM!. Matuschka discusses her breast cancer diagnosis in 1991, her malpractice suit against her doctor, and the art and articles she created as a result. She relates her experiences with different breast cancer and women's organizations in New York City, including SHARE, 1 in 9, the National Organization for Women (NOW), National Alliance of Breast Cancer Organizations (NABCO), and WHAM!. She describes her artwork and the direct actions she helped create at WHAM!, all designed around focusing on bringing people's attention to the realities of breast cancer and educating women from diverse racial, ethnic, and class backgrounds about breast cancer. Matuschka discusses her decision to focus on WHAM! and the differences between WHAM! and SHARE, in particular, including the issues on which each focused and the way each organization functioned.
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cd TW_OH_066_2)
  - Preservation Copy (Box 1, Cd OH-66-010-01)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 091, Cd OH-66-010-01)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_066_ER_17
- Meixell, Elizabeth, January 24, 2004; cuid34415
  Elizabeth Meixell was born in 1945, the oldest of seven children. She attended the State University of New York at Buffalo and moved to New York City in the 1980s. She was a member of Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!).
  This interview was conducted by Tamar Carroll on January 24, 2004 at an unspecified location. The interview details Elizabeth Meixell's involvement with Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) and allied organizations AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP) and the Church Ladies for Choice, the latter being especially important to WHAM!'s activism. Meixell explains that despite being a Roman Catholic and lifelong Republican, she became a pro-choice activist after moving to New York City in the 1980s. She explains that her awareness of left-leaning activism began in the 1970s, as a college student in her 30s at the State University of New York at Buffalo, where she took courses in gender and labor history. Meixell discusses the challenges of organizing demonstrations in New York City and of interacting with law enforcement during protests. She also recalls counterprotests from pro-life organizations, including Lesbians for Life (later the Pro-Life Alliance for Gays and Lesbians).
  This interview contains an anti-Black epithet; it appears on page 16 of the transcript and at 20:32 in the audio.
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cd TW_OH_066_3)
  - Preservation Copy (Box 1, Cd OH-66-003-01)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 091, Cd OH-66-003-01)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_066_ER_18
- Morgan, Tracy, April 5, 2004; cuid34424
  Tracy Morgan was a founding member of Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) and AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP).
  This interview was conducted by Tamar Carroll on April 5, 2004 at an unspecified location. The interview covers Tracy Morgan's involvement in the creation of Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) in 1989, differences in women's rights activism between different generations of activists, how WHAM! solidified the abortion rights movement into the reproductive rights movement, and Morgan's work with AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP), which intertwined with the work being done by WHAM!. Morgan discusses the ways in which WHAM! aimed to have a new activist identity for a younger generation of women's reproductive health activists and WHAM!'s focus on eye-catching demonstrations that used activists's bodies as sites of protest, at times causing arrest. She explains that being involved with ACT UP led her to become an activist for reproductive and sexual health for all, not just for women.
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cd TW_OH_066_4)
  - Preservation Copies (Box 1, Cd OH-66-011-01, OH-66-011-02)
  - Access Copies (Box Shared Tamiment 091, Cd OH-66-011-01, OH-66-011-02)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_066_ER_21
- Ramspacher, Karen, March 5, 2004; cuid34419
  Karen Ramspacher is a reproductive rights activist in New York City. She was an active member of the Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) from 1989-1993, and was also a member of the AIDS Coalition To Unleash Power (ACT UP), the National Abortion Rights Action League (NARAL), Treatment Action Group (TAG), the Reproductive Rights Coalition (RRC), and the Community Health Project. At the time of the interview, Ramspacher worked in the television industry.
  This interview was conducted by Tamar Carroll on March 5, 2004 at an unspecified location. The interview largely focuses on Karen Ramspacher's work as a reproductive rights activist in New York City from 1988 to 1994. Ramspacher's interview revolves around her time as a member of Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!), as well as her association with other New York-based activist groups such as AIDS Coalition To Unleash Power (ACT UP), Church Ladies For Choice, Community Health Project, National Abortion Rights Action League (NARAL), Reproductive Rights Coalition (RRC), and Treatment Action Group (TAG). She discusses beginning her involvement in activist movements shortly after graduating college in 1987, joining ACT UP, and participating in their meetings and actions over the next several years. She explains how inspired by the direct action techniques of ACT UP, she joined the RRC and subsequently became a member of WHAM! in 1989. Ramspacher recounts participating in clinic escorting and defending, but explains that her main focus with WHAM! was organizing public protests and advocating for and performing self-help gynecology. She discusses how her participation in direct activism lessened after 1993, when her time shifted to providing direct care for friends with AIDS. Topics discussed in detail include New York's activist environment in the 1980s and 1990s; social, gender, and generational dynamics within WHAM!; WHAM! actions and organizational structure; and the role of radical politics in activist groups and society.
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cd TW_OH_066_3)
  - Preservation Copies (Box 1, Cd OH-66-006-01, OH-66-006-02)
  - Access Copies (Box Shared Tamiment 091, Cd OH-66-006-01, OH-66-006-02)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_066_ER_19
- Shaw, Susan, July 26, 2004; cuid34420
  Susan Shaw is a former member of Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) and the People with AIDS Coalition. At the time of the interview, she lived in Michigan.